RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In the previous modules, we focused on clustering samples.
In this module, we're going to describe gene clustering.
Now for gene clustering, there's a little bit
of mathematics we can show that can help us interpret the final results.
Now here's the first mathematical formula I want to share with you.
So up here I have the formula for the distance squared.
We can always take the square root at the end.
And what I'm showing you is the distance between two genes,
X and Y in this case.
And then we're moving across M samples.
We are actually standardizing the values.
We're subtracting the mean and dividing by the standard deviation.
Now if we do that, we can work out the math, right?
This is a quadratic, so we square the two terms.
And then we have the multiplication of the two.
This is just simple algebra.
And we work this out, this term is going to be 1,
because the data has been standardized and this
is its standard deviation or its variance, which is 1 by definition.
Same for this one.
And over here we have the correlation.
This is the sample correlation.
So in this case, if you standardize your data
and you compute Euclidean distance, you end up
with a formula that includes just the correlation.
And there's an inverse relationship.
The more correlated two things are, the smaller the distance,
which makes a lot of sense.
Now here's the second formula that's important.
And it's related.
So for this case, what I'm doing is I'm computing
the distance between two genes.
For simplicity of the exposition, I'm going
to assume that X and Y have the same standard deviation and it's 1,
but that they have different means.
So X and Y are two genes.
They move across the samples.
They have standard deviation of 1, but they have different means.
So let's see what their distance is.
So I'm going to work it all out to get the distance in terms of correlation,
just like we did in the previous slide.
So I subtract and add the mean for both genes.
Then I work out the quadratic.
And when I'm finished simplifying this, I get the same result as before,
2 minus 1 minus the correlation.
But because I didn't standardize by removing the mean,
I have this term here.
That's the difference in the means squared.
What is that telling us?
That's telling us that the distance between two genes
is going to be dominated by the differences in mean.
Note that this number is fixed.
It can be at most 2.
This number can be anything.
You can have two genes that are very, very far apart
and the distance is bigger, bigger, and bigger.
Now why is that a problem?
That is a problem because many times we're
looking for genes that move together but aren't
necessarily at exactly the same level.
Genes are not always measured in the same units.
Therefore, we don't necessarily care that they are at different levels.
But we do want to find genes that are, say,
going up and down at the same time.
So for that reason, there's a big difference in the result you will get
if you standardize versus if you don't.
So let me show you some examples with real data.
So here's an example using the data set that we've
used in previous modules, where you have several tissues
and for each tissue we have several biological replicates.
So we took a random sample of 5,000 genes,
just to be able to compute the distance without crashing our computer.
And then we found four clusters using hierarchical clustering.
So now each gene is assigned to one of four clusters.
And you can see what the four clusters are here.
This is the first one.
It's plotted here.
You can see that this seems to be all the genes that are varying around 7,
a value of 7 or so.
Here's another set of genes.
And all that happened here is that we have
another series of genes that are varying around 12.
And here on the fourth cluster, we have a series
of genes that are varying around 10.
So this is really not that interesting.
All these genes are flat.
They're not changing across tissues.
All they're doing is they're changing their mean level.
The distance between the genes in this cluster in this cluster
is driven by their difference in mean, usually not of interest.
So let's repeat the exercise, but this time removing the mean from each gene.
How do we do that?
We have this big table.
For each row we have the values for that gene.
We're going to remove their mean one by one and then re-compute clusters.
Look how different the results are.
So now we have in the first cluster, these are centered at 0.
These are the genes that don't change across tissues.
Now the second cluster, we have genes that slightly changed from the brains
to the rest.
See, there's a little increment there?
This group is now a group that is highly expressed in the brains
and slightly underexpressed in the rest of the tissues.
And then the fourth cluster is a group that is highly expressed in kidney.
We could have shown more clusters and we would
have seen similar patterns that are interesting.
These are genes that go up in liver or up in kidney or down in the brains.
Those are more interesting features of the data.
Therefore in this case, it usually makes more sense
to remove the mean from the genes.
And more importantly, remember that you will get two very different answers
when you use the two different approaches.
All right.
So as a final example, I'm showing you the results
of a very famous experiment, one of the first microarray experiments, where
we recorded gene expression for yeast across our cell cycle.
And you can see this is again de-meaning.
We removed the mean.
We start seeing very interesting patterns,
like genes that follow these cycles, genes that go up,
genes that stay fixed, genes that vary a lot,
genes that have slightly different cycle, et cetera.
So if you are interested in finding things like this,
you are definitely interested in removing the mean from the genes first.