RAFAEL IRIZARRY: We're going to start this module describing hierarchical clustering.
It's one of the many clustering algorithms that exist.
In this figure, we're showing you the result
of applying hierarchical clustering to the data
that we have shown in the previous modules, where
we have several biological replicates for a handful of different tissues.
Now when you look at this figure, you recognize it from the heat map
that we showed at the very beginning of this week's modules.
And this is in fact the technique that is used by heat maps
to organize samples and genes.
So let's describe how hierarchical clustering works.
First step, of course, is to compute a distance between each sample.
Once we've done that, then we're going to start grouping them together.
There's two types of hierarchical clustering, top down and bottom up.
In top down, we start dividing things into groups.
In bottom up, we join things into groups.
So to do this, we need to make another decision.
And it's, how are we going to define the distance between two groups?
There are several ways of doing that, which
I'm not going to cover here in detail.
But you can read about it in any full description of hierarchical clustering.
So we start by finding the two samples that are closest together
and put them into a group.
Then in the next step we find the two closest groups--
a group could be just one sample-- that are closest together
and put those two together.
And we keep doing this repeatedly until we have all samples in one group.
And you can see that.
Just from the picture, you can see that that was what happened here.
You have these two samples were probably put together first.
Then these two, then these two, then these were put together.
Then probably these two were put together and these two, et cetera.
Then we kept going, putting things together all the way up.
Every time you see a split, like this, it
means that these samples, which were already in a group,
were joined with these samples at this particular distance between groups.
This value here is called the height when we do hierarchical clustering.
And then we go all the way to the top, where
all the samples are grouped into just one large group.
Now, some important things to know about this figure.
The first one is that you should think of dendrograms as mobiles.
So consider these two samples.
This is placenta.
And this is colon.
They're next to each other.
But that does not mean that they're close to each other.
The way we find the distance between them is that we go back.
We have to follow the branches all the way to the place where they split,
which is way up here.
So those two samples are actually very far apart.
And we actually saw that in the MDS plot that we showed in a previous module.
I find the MDS plot to be a better way to get
an idea of how far and close things are.
The dendrogram is also useful for that.
So another important characteristic about the dendrogram
is that it doesn't define clusters.
It just groups things.
If we actually want to define clusters, we have to pick a height.
Like for example, I could just draw a line right here.
And now what happens is I keep all the things
below that line that are together, that are in the same group,
and define that as a cluster.
So this is actually quite easy to do in R. And in the labs,
you're going to have several opportunities to try this function.
Now once we are done-- now that we've defined hierarchical clustering,
we can actually explain how heat maps are created.
So here's a heat map with the same data.
You can see again the colors representing the tissues.
And the tissue names are way down here in very small font.
So how is this heat map created?
First, the samples are clustered.
And then the genes are clustered.
Now, because there's 20,000 genes and we don't
want to show a figure with 22,000 rows-- it would also take a long time to run
on the computer-- we actually took a subset of genes.
And the way we did that-- and this is a quite common approach when you're
exploring data-- is we took the variant, we calculated the standard deviation
across sample for every gene.
And we kept the ones that varied the most, because genes
that don't vary too much are probably not changing much.
They're probably not important.
That's not always the case.
But that's one technique that we use in data exploration.
So here we put the top 500 or 200 genes.
And then we clustered all the genes and all the samples.
So we organized the samples according to the clustering.
Then we organized the genes according to the clustering.
So now we have a new ordering of the matrix.
And we show that matrix.
We put colors to signify how high expression there is in each cell.
So in this case, blue means high expression.
White means low expression.
So what do we see here?
What types of things do we see in heat maps?
One is that we can see this group of genes here.
They tend to be highly expressed in this tissue and not in too many others.
And they sort of follow that general pattern.
We also see that these tissues all have these groups
of genes expressed, while the other tissues don't, et cetera.
So we start seeing patterns like this.
It's a very useful exploratory tool for looking at our data
and seeing the structure in our data.
In the next module, we're going to talk a little bit about how variability
makes clustering non-deterministic, a very important fact to remember.