RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Now we&#39;re going to continue the previous analysis,
but now instead of hierarchical clustering,
we&#39;re going to perform k means clustering.
The function kmeans clustering takes a matrix.
It computes the distance on its own.
So we can actually feed it the expression matrix.
We do have to send the transpose because it will compute distances between rows.
All right, the way we use that with a function is also in base,
called kmeans.
And it takes as input, the original matrix.
And again, it&#39;s going to compute distance between rows.
So we have to transpose it.
And now, as we discussed, we have to tell how many clusters we
want it to find.
So let&#39;s say that we have-- to remind ourselves how many tissues we have-- 7,
so we&#39;re going to say 7 centers.
So centers
is equal to 7.
And we don&#39;t know-- we&#39;re going to let kmeans choose
the location of the starting value.
So now that runs kmeans, It&#39;s computing distance,
so it takes a little bit of time, but now it&#39;s done.
And now we can, for example, make again, a table where we see the tissues.
The actual tissues, and the clusters that we got.
So let&#39;s call that clusters, and it&#39;s in the-- the km
object has this component called cluster,
that gives it the different numbers.
Actually look at that, you can see it gives us
a cluster number for each sample.
You can see there how that worked.
So here it is, and we can see it did a pretty good job.
You have cluster number 2.
It&#39;s all colon and placenta, but endometrium got its own.
No mistakes there.
Hippocampus, as well, kidney.
So it worked pretty well at clustering the tissues by group.
Another thing I want to show you is, you can visualize this.
If we&#39;re going to visualize this, we&#39;re going to plot,
so we can use MDS, multi-dimensional scalings,
to be able to plot in two dimensions.
So we&#39;re going to do that, real quick.
That works on d, which we already calculated in the previous video.
If you want to remind yourself why we did that, we just did this.
So that&#39;s how that would work.
We compute that.
We can plot them, and we can see that we can add color
to see the different colors that were clustered here.
So that&#39;s km cluster.
And there you go .
So you can see how these different points got clustered, again.
But these are just two dimensions and there&#39;s more dimensions of that.
So you can see that these are all on top of each other.
It&#39;s hard to see how it would cluster them,
but it&#39;s because there&#39;s other dimensions it&#39;s using
work for this distance calculation.
So that&#39;s how you use the kmeans cluster.
Now one thing I want to show you, is that if you run it again,
you get a different answer.
That&#39;s because it chooses the starting values differently.
You see that one didn&#39;t work as well as the first one.
You get cluster one is-- those are the brains, actually,
but it&#39;s-- you have liver is split now, kidney is split.
So every time you run it-- you can keep running it over and over again
you&#39;re going to see-- you&#39;re going to get different answers every time.
So that&#39;s something important to keep in mind about this function.
That because the starting values are random
it gives you a different answer every time.
You can choose the starting values to avoid that,
but that requires a bit more work on how to decide what starting values to use.
But this is the general idea of how to use kmeans in R.