RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In the previous module, we described a way to account for batch effects
when we know what the batch effects are.
But we also saw evidence for us not really knowing
exactly what the batch effects are.
What are the sources of variability that are affecting our data?
So a more general model would be this surrogate variable model
in where we have, just like before, the outcome of interest, which
in the example that we've been looking at is sex, female or male.
We have measurement error.
But now we have this new term that describes the correlation
that we see between samples.
To simplify this part of the model, we're
assuming that it is determined by a series of columns
that are considered the batches.
So if we only had one batch, one of the columns of w
could just be a series of zeros and ones,
where one means you're in one batch, zero means in the other.
But now, we don't really know who is a zero and who is a one.
And we have to actually estimate that.
So the approach here is difficult because we
don't know what w is, we don't know what alpha is, we don't know what beta is.
All these things have to be estimated, which seems almost impossible to do.
But there is a trick that statisticians have
been using for decades called factor analysis.
So notice that if beta is zero, if the effect of the outcome of interest
is zero, then all we're left with is the sources of variability.
We have the measurement error, and then we
have the effects that are associated with batch,
the surrogate values that we are calling batch effects.
So now the exercise is to find w and alpha.
And by making certain assumptions about how these are uncorrelated
and how they're uncorrelated to noise, we
can actually estimate these w's and these alphas.
And we're going to explain how to do that in the next module, where
we explain singular value decomposition and principal component analysis.