RAFAEL IRIZARRY: So in the last module we presented this model.
This is the model that procedures such as surrogate variable analysis uses.
Now the problem is we don't know W. We don't know alpha.
We don't know k.
We don't know beta.
We have to estimate all these things.
This is not straightforward.
And I'm going to show you just one of the algorithms that
tries to fit this model, which is the algorithm that
implements the surrogate variable analysis.
So here's the idea.
Here's a data set that has real signal.
Up here you can see the real signal versus not.
And it has some batches.
So here's Batch 1 is the one that's dark, 1, 2, 3, 4.
That's Batch 1.
And then the light is Batch 2.
That's the batch we don't know.
It's hidden.
We don't know that it's there.
We want to estimate it.
So you can see over here this is the true batch, which you don't know.
We have to try to find it.
So you have the first two arrays are in Batch 1.
The next two arrays are in Batch 2, the next five, cetera.
See the pattern?
When you're up, you're dark.
When you're down, you're light.
So we want to estimate this.
So here's the approach.
In the first step, we use the singular value decomposition
trick to just try to estimate a batch.
Though in this case, I'm only showing you the first column
that we're estimating.
And here's the result.
You can see the estimated batch.
It's not quite right.
But it's kind of getting there already.
So here's the truth.
Here's our first estimate.
So now what we do is we assume that this is correct.
And we find genes that are associated with this current estimate
of the batch.
And we're going to give them weights.
So here are the weights for the genes that
are correlated with this version of the batch.
You can see it kind of makes sense.
These genes have strong correlations.
You have this guy, that guy, this guy.
So it seems like it's working pretty well.
And all these other ones get 0 weight.
So now we use only these genes to estimate the batch again,
using factor analysis or singular value decomposition.
Here's the data that we're going to use, because we're only
giving weight to these genes.
And now it gets a little better.
It gets a little closer to the truth.
So what do we do next?
We repeat.
Again we give weights.
And we repeat the analysis.
And in the next step, we get pretty close to the truth.
So that's the idea behind SVA.
There's now many competitors that are performing very well as well.
We're going to include some of those links
to the papers and software on our class web page.
So now let's see what happens with our example data
that we showed in the previous models after we implement SVA.
So here are the autosome genes that we think should be a flat p value.
We don't think there should be signal there.
And here are the chromosome Y genes.
This is before SVA.
Now we apply SVA.
In this case, it estimates k to be 5.
And it estimates columns.
We stick it into the limma procedure to get estimates of the coefficients
and standard errors of these coefficients.
We recompute p values.
And look at how it looks now.
The histogram is pretty close to flat.
However, we did not lose what we believe to be the real genes.
So what is it that we did here, just to review?
We started out with a data set that clearly
had real signal due to the different sexes.
It clearly had some structure that was batch-related.
And then it had noise.
We estimated each one of these components with SVA.
And we can actually make pictures splitting that up
into the four components.
All right.
So here's the data as decomposed by SVA.
We have the original data.
We have the signal part, the part having to do with the outcome of interest.
Then we have the surrogate variable part, or the batch effect part.
And then we have the residuals.
So we can see that in this case SVA did quite well.
Now with that said, it's important to keep in mind
that current solutions to batch effects don't solve all batch effect problems.
We're faced with situations with real data
where SVA and many other algorithms actually fail to detect all the batches
or they over-correct.
So you always want to do a lot of exploratory data analysis
and post-analysis diagnostics to make sure
that your answers make sense in some way.
But another thing that is important to mention
is that you want to be as careful as possible
when designing your experiment to avoid too much confounding.
One of the situations in which all these methods fail
is when a batch is heavily confounded with your outcome of interest.
It becomes very difficult to separate the signal from the batch.
So you want as much as possible to either balance or randomize
the experiment so that you don't have this problem.
Now even when you do balance the experiment,
there is still unwanted variability that reduces your power.
So even in those cases when there are batch effects present,
you do want to implement some of these methods
to improve your ability to extract signal from your data.