RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In the previous module, we showed you this model.
That is the naive model we would fit if we were
interested in finding differences between males and females.
But it's not accounting for batch effects.
So how can we do that?
One of the first approaches suggested for genomics data
is a method called ComBat.
What ComBat does is it adds a row to the X
matrix that accounts for batch effects.
In this case, you have to know what the batch effects are.
In this case we know there's June and October.
So we're going to go ahead and add that covariate to the model.
In this case it would be on the third row
and we would have zeros for June, ones for October.
Then we add in a beta that will account for the fact that some genes are
affected by the batch and others aren't.
So when you do this, now you can estimate the parameters of interest--
in this case, it would be the beta ones-- taking into account the batch.
And if we do that and recalculate the
p-values that we calculated in the previous module, which are shown here.
So we were worried about the fact that we have too many genes
differentially expressed in the autosomes, and we apply ComBat,
we get slight improvement.
You see how this height dropped but the histogram on the right
didn't change much?
Which we don't want.
We don't want that to change, because these we believe are real differences.
But it's not completely flat.
And we wonder if maybe we haven't removed the entirety of the variation
due to batches.
So the limitation of ComBat is that it requires the user
to supply the batch effects.
In most cases we use the processing date.
However, my experience has shown me that processing date is just
a surrogate for other sources of variability.
And there's more to it than just date.
And we can't always know what is there.
Just to show you how that's a possibility here,
if we look at the dates, these are the dates
of all the samples in this complete data set,
not just the smaller set we constructed.
You can see that although there's some natural jumps,
there are also some slow movements.
You have one, a few done each day.
Then there's a jump.
So where do we split this to define batches?
In the smaller data set that we constructed, where we have 12 and 12,
you can see that the summer arrays and the fall arrays also
have days in between.
Here we have three days, here we have two days.
And maybe the mornings are different from the afternoons.
Many things can be happening here that we haven't annotated.
So how can we account for that?
In the next module, we're going to talk about factor analysis, singular value
decomposition, and then SVA as a solution to this problem.