RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Once we understand the singular value decomposition,
we&#39;re ready to explain what principal component analysis is.
We&#39;re going to use this example that we&#39;ve used before with twin heights.
Each point represents the height of a twin 1 versus the height of twin 2.
And it&#39;s represented as a matrix that has n rows and two columns.
And the task that is related to principal component analysis
is to find a projection.
We&#39;re going to find a vector that defines that projection.
Here we&#39;re going to call it V1.
That is orthogonal, so the cross product of V1 is 1.
And it maximizes the sum of squares of that projection, which
can be written as shown in this last equation here-- y projected to V1.
You take the cross product of that.
That gives you the sum of squares.
We want to find a vector that maximizes that variability.
What we&#39;re going to see-- we&#39;re going to try out
different Vs to motivate why it is that we end up with the optimal solution.
And it turns out that the optimal solution can be obtained
using the singular value decomposition.
So let&#39;s just try out some V&#39;s so you get an idea what&#39;s happening here.
So the first V we&#39;re going to try is simply 1, 0.
So that&#39;s the vector.
And when you project the data onto that vector,
you basically get back the height of twin 1.
You multiply y by v. The first dimension is kept,
and the second one is multiplied by 0.
It goes away.
And we can easily compute the sum of squares for the first dimension,
and we get the number you can see at the top of the figure here.
Now, can we do better than that?
So let&#39;s just try something else.
Let&#39;s try the vector 1 minus 1.
Can we even use that one?
Well, we can&#39;t, because the cross product is not 1.
So we can easily fix that by dividing by the square root 2.
Now it does have that property.
And we&#39;re going to try this vector v. That
is basically giving us the difference, but standardized
to have an orthogonal transformation.
So if we use this, now what we&#39;re doing is projecting each point
to the space that is spanned by v, which is shown
with a diagonal line you see there.
Now we project each point, and we get the orange dots on that line.
Those are the projections.
So that&#39;s y multiplied by v. And we can take the sum of squares.
That&#39;s easy to do.
We just take the cross product.
And in this case, we get a much smaller value than we did before.
So this is definitely not a solution.
So we can mathematically show that the solution to this problem, the v that
maximizes this, is 1 divided by the square root of 2,
1 divided by the square root of 2, as shown here.
We have seen this vector before in our videos on singular value decomposition.
And this one has a very high cross product.
When you map each point to the space spanned by v,
you can see that it has a wide range.
And it turns out that this is the solution.
So this vector that we&#39;ve just shown is the vector
that maximizes the sum of squares of yv 1, transposed yv 1.
And it&#39;s referred to as a first principal component.
That&#39;s what this V1 is.
It&#39;s also called an eigenvector.
And then y times V1 are the projection or the coordinates or eigenvalues.
These are just mathematical terminology.
But note that each row of y gets a coordinate, just
one value for each row of y in the example that we&#39;ve shown.
Now, to get the second principal component, what we do
is we take the residuals of-- we subtract--
you can call it an approximation of y based
just on that vector V1, as shown in this formula here.
And now with those residuals, you try to find a second vector that maximizes
the cross product for the residuals.
And then if we had more dimensions than two-- if we had m dimensions,
then we would keep going and get the third and fourth and fifth, et
cetera, using this procedure.
And that basically defines a principal component technique.
That&#39;s how you find them.
And again, you can find these using the singular value decomposition,
as shown in this code.
If we apply it, you can see it right here-- if we apply the singular value
decomposition to y, you can see that we get these two
vectors that we showed you earlier.