RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In this module, we're going to start showing you
how you can model data that has batch effects in it.
And that'll eventually take us to solutions
to estimating differences of interest in data that has batches.
So to do that, we're going to construct a data set.
This is real data.
But it was constructed in a somewhat artificial way.
We took the data set from the previous module, where
we had the two ethnicities.
We stuck to one ethnicity, but took two batches.
June, 2005, October, 2005.
And then for each one, we picked males and females in a way
that they were confounded with date, but not completely confounded with date.
So you can see that on the table on the left.
So June had more males.
October had more females.
This is something we don't recommend doing
if you're designing an experiment.
But sometimes you just get data this way and you have to deal with it.
So you can see an image of a subset of the genes.
So the first 12 are the females.
The second 12 are the males.
The first few genes are genes from the Y chromosome, where
we know that there are some differences between males and females.
So there is some real signal there.
And you can already kind of see it.
You see some red as high expressed versus
blue, low expressed, males versus females.
Then we took a set, shown down here, where
the genes were associated with batch.
So they changed from June to October.
And you can see here this must be June, the orange, and this is June.
And the blue is October.
And vice versa down here.
So you know within the females there's three in June and nine in October.
In the men three in October and nine in June.
And then we selected some random genes as well.
So this is just an illustration.
This is not-- we actually analyzed the entire data set.
But for many of the pictures in this module,
we're actually showing just these genes.
So how do we begin to model this?
Well, let's start with a naive model.
So in the naive model, we write something like this.
We have a matrix that has features-- genes, SNPs, DNA methylation, loci.
And on the columns, we have samples.
So we have the 12 females and the 12 males.
So that's represented here with this Y. There's m features and n samples.
In most statistics textbooks, you're going
to see the transpose of this matrix used.
So don't be confused by that.
We use it in this form here because that's
how we usually handle the data on the computer.
And we don't want to get confused between what we do in the computer
and what we show in class.
But when you go read a textbook, you might see it the other way.
You might see why Y n m.
And the data matrix will be transposed.
All right.
So now that's the data.
So in the naive model, we're going to say, well, there's a sex effect.
And that would be modeled with a matrix that
has 0s for the females and 1s for the males.
And then each gene will have a male effect.
So that would be in a matrix like this one
that would have the betas, the parameters of interest.
And then we have another matrix that has the covariates.
And then we have some noise.
So that's also an m by n matrix.
So X is a simple matrix.
It's easy to understand.
X is basically denoting who's a male and who's a female.
It's going to be a 2 by n by 24 in this case matrix.
And the first row is going to have just 1s that
will denote the gene mean level.
And in the second row, it's going to have either a 0 or 1,
depending if you're a male or a female.
So you'll have 0, 0, 0, 12 0s, followed by 12 1s.
Very simple matrix.
There's two betas for each gene.
The first one is the mean level.
The second one is the effect of being male.
So what we're after here if we're thinking of imitating a real analysis,
we're looking for genes for which beta 1 is not 0.
Those will be the interesting ones.
Those will be genes where males and females are different.
In this particular data set, we expect this to only
be happening on the Y chromosome and maybe the X,
because some genes escape X inactivation.
All right.
So this model, we've seen it before.
It's the one we've used in the linear model modules.
But in this case, it's missing something.
This model is going to explain this variability up here,
because when beta 1 is different from 0, you
will get differences between the females and the males.
But this down here is not explained by that.
So we need a way to explain this.
So basically, if we fit the model we just showed,
which is equivalent to running a t-test on each gene,
we get many genes with small p values, more than expected,
for the autosome genes.
And we suspect that that's wrong.
Then on chromosome Y genes, we get most of the genes differentially expressed,
which is something we expect.
On this histogram on the right, we want to see
a lot of genes that are differentially expressed.
But we suspect that the histogram on the left should just be flat.
We just picked randomly the males and the females.
There shouldn't be many differences outside of these chromosomes.
So we suspect that these genes here are actually due to the batch effect.
So in the next modules, we're going to show you
two different approaches, ComBat and SVA, that adjust for batch effects
and hopefully improve the results.