RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In this short video, I&#39;m
going to introduce the concept of smoothing.
So in machine learning, one of the tasks that we very commonly
are trying to perform is to estimate either the conditional probability
of an outcome given predictors or the expected
value of an outcome given predictors.
So here, I&#39;m denoting that with E of Y given X. So that&#39;s
what we&#39;re going to estimate.
And this particular data set I&#39;m showing you,
which is actually a real data set-- it&#39;s data from microarrays.
I&#39;m comparing two samples in an MA plot, Y is M, X is a.
And we see a non-linear dependent of Y on X.
And as we&#39;ll learn in future videos, actually in the Bioconductor course,
is that we need to normalize this data.
And to do that we have to find this curve, this dependence,
so we can remove it.
So that&#39;s the motivation for this particular example.
So we see this data, and we think there&#39;s an underlying curve
and then there&#39;s random noise around that curve.
And we have a suspicion.
There&#39;s reasons to believe that this bias is actually
a smooth function of x.
So we want to estimate Y given X. And the standard approach,
when we have two variables of using linear regression,
is not going to work here.
We see the regression that&#39;s been fitted to this data,
and we immediately see that there is a bias.
At the beginning, there&#39;s more positive residuals, shown in green,
and in the middle, there&#39;s more negative residuals, shown in purple.
And then there&#39;s, at the end, again, some green residuals.
That&#39;s because the underlying curve appears to be non-linear.
It&#39;s more like a check mark shape.
So the idea of smoothing is based, in a way,
in Taylor&#39;s theorem that tells us that if you look at any function,
no matter how complicated it is, if you look at it close,
in small little intervals, it can be approximated with a lower degree
polynomial.
So in this case, I&#39;m assuming that if you look at a small enough window,
you can assume that it has a mean constant.
So the purple points in this small little interval,
they almost appear as if there is no dependence
of Y on X in that very small window.
We&#39;re assuming that the function, the underlying function E expected
value of Y given X, is constant in this small interval.
So we do that.
We do that for other intervals as well.
Here&#39;s another interval where we see that the mean shifts.
It&#39;s now a little bit lower.
So now the idea bin smoothing, for example,
is to move around, move the center of these bins across the entire range of X
and estimate that mean and keep that mean as the estimate of E of Y given X.
So we can see that we&#39;re almost tracing the curve that in our minds
is the curve that should be there.
That&#39;s what bin smoothing does.
Now when we look at the final result of bin smoothing,
it looks a little jagged.
It&#39;s not as smooth as we were-- at least I was hoping it to be.
Now, that&#39;s because this approximation of using a constant in a small window
is not always appropriate.
The data&#39;s moving too fast, we have to make the windows too small,
and then we have too few points to obtain precision of our estimates.
So local regression, local weighted regression, which is nicknamed LOESS,
is a method that instead of fitting constants, it fits lines or parabolas.
And it has other properties.
Like it tries to remove outliers.
But the main one is that we fit lines to small windows.
Now we don&#39;t have to make the windows so small because--
and this is actually something that Taylor&#39;s theorem tells us--
if give the degree of the polynomial is bigger,
we can actually expand the window a little bit.
So you can think of this as forming an edge in gardening,
where you want to form a curve, and you have a shovel that is straight edged.
But you can form curves with straight edges.
And that&#39;s what we&#39;re going to do here.
So you fit a line to these windows, and then you move the window along,
and you get another fitted line.
And you keep the center of that line as an estimate.
And here&#39;s an animation showing us how that works.
And now it&#39;s giving us a fit that is much better looking than the bin
smoother, in part, because we&#39;re now using bigger windows, more data, more
precise estimates.
And at the end, we get a nice-looking curve
like this that appears to have captured the bias.
And we can remove that bias away and improve our data.
Now what if the data&#39;s multi-dimensional?
So here&#39;s an example.
Now the expected value of Y given X comma X2, so two dimensions,
is shown here.
Now I&#39;m not showing you data.
I&#39;m actually showing you the expected value, the conditional expectation of Y
given these two variables, X1 and X2.
So color means higher value.
Sorry.
Blue means lower values, red means higher values.
So we&#39;re showing you that function.
We want to estimate that function with data.
So here&#39;s some data.
And from this data, we now want to estimate that underlying expectation
that we don&#39;t know, we want to estimate.
So here again we can use the same idea.
We can form small windows, and in that window,
either estimate a plane or a constant plane or maybe a parabolic curve.
And we do it for several locations.
We can do it there, there.
We can actually do it for every single location and obtain an estimate.
In fact, if we do this, we&#39;re doing something
very similar to k nearest neighbors.
All right.
So here&#39;s k nearest neighbors with 50.
We estimate the mean value by taking votes across zeros and ones.
So that data that I showed you originally, the points were-- red
meant 1 and blue meant 0.
So in this particular case, we&#39;re basically
voting for either red or blue.
But then we get a proportion of reds, proportion of blues.
And that proportion is shown in this plot as an estimate of E of Y
given X1 and X2.
And you can see that it does a pretty good job.
This is a very simple approach of k nearest neighbors.
But again, the idea is to look at smaller bins
where we think the data is closer to either constant or a plane or a simpler
polynomial that we can fit, and then move that window around
to obtain an estimate of the more complicated curve.
So that&#39;s smoothing, a very short introduction to smoothing.
And that should help us better understand
some of what we do in other machine learning techniques.