RAFAEL IRIZARRY: So what we&#39;re after is estimating the conditional probability of Y
equals 1 given x1 and x2.
There are many, many approaches to doing that.
And in this module, we&#39;re going to cover one call K-nearest neighbors.
It&#39;s one of the most simple ones and more intuitive ones.
So the very, very simple idea is the following.
You have an x.
You&#39;re given an x, which in this case is a point in two-dimensional space.
You have two genes, x1 and x2.
And what we&#39;re going to do is we&#39;re going
to take the K-nearest points in the observed data.
We&#39;re going to take the K-nearest points to that x.
And each one of those is going to be either a 0 or a 1.
We&#39;re going to take the average of those 0s and 1s.
This is sometimes called voting.
Each point gets to vote.
And that average is going to be our prediction.
So let&#39;s see what happens if we take K equals to 1.
This is kind of an absurd case.
If we take x equal to 1, then basically the closest point to x
is going to be itself.
And you&#39;re going to be either 0 or 1, depending on what the observed data is.
So here is the map that&#39;s formed when you use K equals 1 nearest neighbor.
And you see a very choppy estimate.
You have islands of orange over here and islands of purple over here.
However, when you compute the error rate not surprisingly in the training set
it&#39;s 0, because every point it&#39;s its closest and it&#39;s going to be the same.
So you get them all right.
However, on the test set, there&#39;s a very different story.
Now the error rate goes all the way up to 37.5.
And you can see several cases where you have these little islands that
are orange and inside them you have several purple points.
That&#39;s because that region was called orange simply
because in the training set there was one solitary orange point up there.
OK.
So K equals 1 is just not a great choice.
But we can use other values.
For example, let&#39;s take the nearest 100 points.
If we do that, now we get something that looks much better.
You can see that the estimated prediction function now
splits the space into this orange part and this purple part.
And you can see that it&#39;s non-linear.
It&#39;s different from the linear model.
The error rate now is 24.5.
This is on the training set.
And on the test set, it&#39;s a very respectable 28.0.
This is much better than the linear model approach
that we saw in a previous module.
So let&#39;s see why that is.
Why does K-nearest neighbor work so much better than the linear model approach?
So here&#39;s the truth.
You have the orange area and the purple area.
This is the true probability function when it&#39;s smaller than 1/2
and when it&#39;s larger than 1/2.
And over here is the best estimate you get with a linear model.
It&#39;s constrained to be split by a line.
There&#39;s just no way around that.
If your model is linear in the way we defined
it to be when we tried this approach, you have to have it split by a line,
because the cases where the function is equal to 1/2
is by mathematical definition a straight line.
So you have no way of creating an estimate that looks like this.
Now K-nearest neighbor is much more flexible.
And now you get something closer to the truth.
Now you&#39;re basically saying-- the basic idea behind K-nearest neighbors
it&#39;s similar to the idea behind loess.
We have a neighborhood of points.
We assume that in that neighborhood the function is flat.
It&#39;s a small neighborhood.
And we estimate it with a mean.
And then we start moving that neighborhood around
to get a final result that looks like this.
Now with that said, you can see that we don&#39;t necessarily
have to make it just a flat line.
We could have fit parabolas or other functions, other kernels.
And we might have even gotten a better answer than this.
All right.
Now one last important point to make.
When you have noisy data, as you do in genomics,
it is going to be very rare where you&#39;re going to make perfect predictions.
In fact in this case that I just showed you,
it&#39;s impossible to make perfect predictions.
On average, the best possible classifier,
which is called a Bayes classifier-- this
is what you predict when you know the truth, when
you know what the true conditional expectation is.
Even that perfect case scenario produces errors.
Why?
Because the data is noisy.
There are cases with the same x1 and x2 that are 0 and 1.
Two different cases, same gene expression for two genes.
One&#39;s a 0.
One&#39;s a 1.
That&#39;s just random variability.
In those cases, you can&#39;t possibly predict them perfectly.
So in this plot, I just want to show you the two points here.
One is the how optimistic error rates from the training set
are-- this is for K-nearest neighbors-- and how close
we can get to the best possible prediction based
on the Bayes classifier.
So what this plot is showing you is the error rates, based on just one sample--
remember, this is not the theoretical value.
This is what we get from this one example
with one sample that&#39;s test and one example that&#39;s training.
These are the error rates we get down here
in pink color for the training set.
And you can see that with K-nearest neighbors with one neighbor
you get apparently perfect prediction.
But when you go to the test set, it goes all the way up to 37.
So here what I&#39;m doing is I&#39;m changing the K in the K-nearest neighbors from 2
all the way to 200.
And you can see that the optimistic prediction error is worse.
It&#39;s most optimistic, most incorrectly optimistic for smaller values of K,
not surprisingly, because we have too much flexibility.
But the actual error rate on the test set is actually dropping with K.
Now at some point, it starts going up again.
And that&#39;s because now the model is not flexible enough.
And we&#39;re not able to capture the nonlinearity
in the true conditional probability.
So that is an important lesson to take away,
that training and test errors are very different.
It&#39;s very important to look at test error rates to evaluate your models.
So in the next module, we&#39;re going to introduce
the concept of cross-validation.
Cross-validation is a technique that permits
you to obtain good estimates of the error rates
you will get when you&#39;re given a new data set to predict.
You should be aware that there&#39;s many other approaches to prediction.
K-nearest neighbor is just one.
Five examples of techniques that are very widely used
are linear discriminant analysis, or LDA; neural networks; support vector
machines; classification algorithm and regression trees,
or CART; and random forests.
All these methods are implemented in R packages
so you can actually use them with your data to create prediction algorithms.