RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In this video, we&#39;re going
to show you how to compute distance in R. We&#39;re going to use this data set
that we have been using as an example.
It includes gene expression measurements for 189 samples on about 22,000 genes,
and it is-- let&#39;s look at that real quick.
It&#39;s saved in the object e, and each column represents a tissue.
These are from the public repositories.
Each tissue is very likely from a different person,
and we can look at which tissue each column represents
by looking at this vector tissue that just lists them out
as a character vector.
So we can see we have several tissues.
We can use a function table and see how much of each one we have.
All right, now let&#39;s go straight in to calculating distances.
Let&#39;s say we want to compute the distance between two samples.
Let&#39;s take two at random, take the first two.
That&#39;s the first column, represents the first sample, and then the second,
and I&#39;m going to pick a third at random, 87.
Now, let&#39;s see what those tissues are just
to see what we&#39;re working with here.
They are two kidneys and a colon, so we expect the first two
to be closer to each other than the last one because they&#39;re different issues.
And their gene expression profile, these points,
are expected to be closer if they&#39;re the same tissue.
So how do we compute distance?
Well, the formula we showed in class tells us we
take the difference between each entry of x and y,
square that and then take the sum.
That gives us the square of the distance, so we take the square root
and that should be it.
That should give us the distance between x and y.
Let&#39;s see if that works.
It says it&#39;s 85.8546.
Now, let&#39;s look at the same thing for the distance
between the first and third tissue, and we get 122.
As expected, it&#39;s a bigger number.
All right, in the videos, we also showed how we can use matrix algebra.
So we take x minus y, define that as a difference
and then take the cross product of that with itself, we
should get the same answer.
So let&#39;s try it.
I would write crossprod and then just x minus y.
It&#39;s that simple.
Now, we have to take the square root of that
and that should give us 85.8546 because it&#39;s the same calculation.
And there it is, and we can do the same for y minus z
and again, get the same answer.
Great.
Now, if we wanted to compute the distances between each pair of samples,
there&#39;s a function that does that and it&#39;s called dist.
So we can look at the help file for dist, and there it is.
And we can read that and see that it computes
the distance between every row in x.
So we would apply that to e, but we want the distance between each column,
those are the samples.
And the way we do achieve that is by taking the transpose so
that the rows are columns, and now we get the distance between each column.
Let&#39;s put that into d.
A word of warning.
If I type dist of e without the transpose,
I might crash my R session, because we&#39;re
asking R to compute the distance between 22,215, choose two pairs.
So every pair of genes, that&#39;s a big number.
So to store all that information, we have to create a gigantic object.
You might not have enough memory for that.
But here we&#39;re taking the transpose, that should give us a 189
by 189 matrix of distances.
Remember, for each pair we have a distance, each pair of columns
gives us a distance.
Now, this is an object of class dist.
It isn&#39;t that easy to work with.
If we want to extract things like the distance between the first two samples,
what I do is I turn it into a matrix and then use it as a matrix.
And once it&#39;s turned into a matrix, now entry 1, 2
gives us the distance between the first and the second column,
so that should be 85.8546, and there is.
And then the same thing for the entry 1-- what was it?
87.
That should be 122, I think it was.
And there it is.
OK, so that&#39;s how this function dist works.
It&#39;s very useful.
I use it often.
One other thing I wanted to show you.
Is that if you wanted to visualize all the distances,
you could use the image function and just type as.matrix.d, and you&#39;re
going to get a color image of all the distances,
so that&#39;s that 189 by 189 matrix.
The top triangle and the bottom triangle should be the same
because the distance between x and y is the same
as the distance between y and x.
And you can see these red squares.
Those red squares are there because the samples are somewhat
ordered by tissue so you have tissues that
are close on the matrix are also close in biology or biology wise close,
and then you get these reddish squares representing the distance
between tissues of the same kind.
Red is smaller and yellow is larger.
OK, so that&#39;s how we compute distance using R.