RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In this video, we&#39;re going
to demonstrate how to implement hierarchical clustering in R.
So we&#39;re going to demonstrate it using the tissue gene expression data.
And we&#39;re going to start right away.
The first thing we have to do is get a distance between each column.
For that, we can use the dist function.
We&#39;ve already covered that.
And because I want it on the columns of the expression matrix,
I have to transpose that matrix.
Because by default, distance computes distance between rows.
So now I have the distance.
And the next step is to apply hierarchical clustering
using these distances.
For that, I have a function in base-- you
don&#39;t have to load any new package-- called hclust.
And that, it&#39;s that simple.
Now we have applied hierarchical clustering to these samples
through the distance matrix d.
This is an object of class hclust.
And functions like plot know what to do with this object right away.
It knows it&#39;s a hierarchical clustering object, and it makes a dendrogram.
Right now, that dendrogram isn&#39;t very informative for a couple reasons.
One is that instead of tissue-- not names.
We&#39;re showing the column names, which are very hard to interpret.
Second, the font is too big, and they&#39;re riding on top of each other.
Both those things are relatively easy to fix.
First, we&#39;ll change the font to a smaller one, so we can see something,
and second, we&#39;re going to use as labels the tissue.
Now remember this vector tissue is in the correct order, and so they match.
The entries of tissue match the columns of the original e-matrix.
And this function plot, when applied to hierarchical clustering object,
it keeps track of that.
So it&#39;ll put the right label here according
to the position of that label in this vector and what sample this is.
So if I do that, you can now see that we have clustered the different tissues.
You can see we see liver here, so you already see some clustering
based on the tissue column.
It&#39;s not that easy to read, but you can see a kidney.
And there&#39;s hippocampus here, et cetera.
So that&#39;s how easy it is.
I&#39;m going to show you a quick way to add colors
to this-- the rafalib package-- we&#39;ve included
a function that lets you add that.
Make the same plot adding color.
It&#39;s called the-- what is it called-- it&#39;s called-- hard
to pronounce name-- it&#39;s the myplclust.
That&#39;s because plclust is the original one built for hierarchical clustering
objects.
Myplclust.
And now I can add-- I&#39;ll use these same parameters-- now
I can add color to the labels using the lab.col.
And now I have to give a number, so that each tissue
has its own number thus color.
So there&#39;s a function also in rafalib that turns characters
into factors and then into numbers.
And we&#39;ve named that as fumeric().
So if you send tissue to that, it&#39;ll turn each tissue
into a different number.
So now I should be ready to-- label there-- I should be ready to run this,
and we should see colors now.
Whoops.
I have to load the package.
All right.
So there they are.
And you can now see that these livers here are together,
and then the colons are together, kidneys, and another tissue here--
a hippocampus cerebellum.
Now the brains are a little bit mixed up.
And we also have a couple of kidneys in here,
and cerebellum, and liver, and this strange little cluster.
But now, one thing we discussed in the previous videos
is that hierarchical clustering groups samples.
It doesn&#39;t really give us clusters.
It just tells us how far things are through a dendrogram.
We actually want to split them into discrete clusters.
We have to cut the tree.
So for example, I could cut the tree at a specific height, for example, 120.
If I add a line there, you can see that what I&#39;m doing now
is-- I&#39;ll say anything that splits below that line
is going to be in the same group.
So all these here will be the same group.
All these here, they split up here.
All the other splits happen down here.
They&#39;ll all be in the same group.
So we can apply that to the hierarchical clustering object using the cutree()
function.
It does it automatically.
And my height is going to be 120.
This function, by the way, you can also send it
the number of clusters you want, and it figures out the height for you.
So I&#39;ll put this into clusters.
And now I have-- for each sample, I have a cluster, a number.
You see all these numbers.
So let&#39;s see how that would have worked if we did not know these were tissues,
and we just wanted to cluster and see if there&#39;s any discovery, any biology.
Would we discover the different tissues?
This does a pretty good job of doing that.
Show you that with a table that shows us that, for example, let&#39;s
look at the good ones first.
Almost all the livers are in the cluster 8.
And there&#39;s no other tissue type in cluster 8.
It&#39;s all livers.
Now there&#39;s a couple of weirdos here.
Another one that works well is colon.
See colon.
There we make no mistakes.
We would have discovered all the colons at its own cluster.
And there&#39;s other examples where they&#39;re in two clusters--
so the hippocampus and the kidneys-- not to the kidneys
are-- and the kidneys are in separate clusters,
but there&#39;s no other tissues in those clusters, so that worked OK.
The places where we are don&#39;t do that well are things like kidney that
are spread across different ones.
And cerebellum are also split across different clusters.
So that&#39;s how you use that hierarchical clustering function.
It&#39;s very simple, very quick.
And most of it is in the base packages, so you don&#39;t really
even have to load new packages to perform this analysis.