RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In this video, we&#39;re going to show you
how to do exploratory data analysis with a PCA.
And the first thing we&#39;re going to do is load and fix
a data set-- a public data set so it has all this information we
need to do further analyses.
That is not important for what we&#39;re explaining here,
so you can follow along with the text later, if you want.
Right now, we&#39;re going to go straight to obtaining
the SVD of y, which includes the scaled data for this gene expression
experiment, which has the samples for several ethnic groups
that we know were recorded across different time points.
So one of things we then do is look at the image plot of the correlations,
and we see it&#39;s a quite complicated one.
You see these blocks that seemed to be showing
the correlation of certain samples is higher than across other samples.
So what is that?
What&#39;s going on there?
If we had random data, it would look-- the d&#39;s of the singular value
composition would basically look flat in comparison to what
you get with our data set, showing us that there is indeed
quite a bit of structure here.
OK, so the first thing we&#39;re going to show-- we can show here--
is we&#39;ve already computed the singular value decomposition,
so we can very quickly make an MDS plot.
And one of the things we often do in exploration
is we use color to show the different factors,
different covariates in the MDS plot.
So here, I&#39;m making an MDS plot with just two dimensions,
and I&#39;m showing you the three different ethnic groups with color.
So I can add a legend there to know which is which, and immediately we
see that there&#39;s a lot of variability in orange-- in the first PC
more than the others, which makes us a little suspicious that maybe there&#39;s
something else going on here.
And now-- so what we&#39;re going to do now is instead of showing
ethnic group as a color, we&#39;re going to show the year in which it
was processed with color.
So we have-- here&#39;s the years.
We can see it&#39;s confounded with the ethnic group.
So we&#39;re going to make that plot now.
Colors is now going to represent years, and we see
that it also is very much correlated.
All right, so look at that, those two plots.
There&#39;s the legend with dates, and here&#39;s with ethnic groups.
So all we&#39;re doing is changing the color,
so clearly there&#39;s a lot of correlation with both year and ethnic group.
They&#39;re confounded so that we don&#39;t know which is which.
So something we can do to explore this further is to make box plots of the PCs
and split them by a outcome that we think is related to batch.
So year is one, but now we can get a little bit more specific and use months
instead of year.
Because we&#39;re making a box plot, you&#39;ll see how it-- what we&#39;re trying to do
is to further explain variability.
If we can explain with month, then it really
points to it being a problem of processing and not so much biology
that&#39;s driving these differences.
So here we define the month.
This is a nice function that lets us extract a month from a date.
You can look that up, learn more about how that works.
So we have 21 unique months, so now what I&#39;m going to do
is I&#39;m going to find the variable month and I&#39;m
going to split-- let&#39;s start with the first-- I&#39;m going to define i1.
That&#39;s the first principal component here.
We can make a box plot, and look at that.
Now, I&#39;m going to add points.
So we can see how the first PC very much correlates with month,
further confirming that this is probably what&#39;s driving the variability.
We can actually do that for more than one PC.
We can see that the first four PCs actually
correlate with month pretty strongly.
So a lot of the structure that we&#39;re seeing
is probably driven somehow by a batch effect
that seems to be related to the time in which the array was processed.
So you can do more systematic looks at this.
You can try things like ANOVA to see which PCs are actually
correlating with month or other factors that you think are
related to some kind of batch effect.
But here what we&#39;ve shown is how you can use
a PCA to do exploratory data analysis.
And another thing that this helps us with is we can start getting an idea--
if we are going to use, say, factor analysis,
it starts to give us an idea of how many factors
we need to describe the structure that we see in the data.