RAFAEL IRIZARRY: To explain the singular value decomposition,
we&#39;re going to continue using the twin height example.
Shown here on the left, the data is shown.
We&#39;re plotting the two heights in a scatter plot.
And then on the right, we&#39;re showing the rotation
that we already found to have the property that it
can be used to reduce the dimension if, for example, we
want to preserve distance considering only one dimension.
So in this case, Z1 is the dimension that does that.
The transformation we&#39;re applying is shown down here.
So we&#39;re going to see how this relates to the singular value decomposition.
Turns out that you can get this transformation using singular value
decomposition.
So lets look at what it is, what the singular value decomposition
is in general.
We can write any matrix m x n matrix Y with three other matrices,
U, V, and D. U and V are orthogonal and D is diagonal.
And they have the property that U transpose Y equals DV transpose.
And we&#39;re going to see why that&#39;s powerful when we apply this to data.
And a very important characteristic is that the sum of squares of VD or UD
are decreasing.
That&#39;s going to be a key useful fact that we use, for example, for dimension
reduction.
And I&#39;ll note that the more common way to represent this transformation
is shown down here.
It&#39;s equivalent to this form that I find slightly more interpretable.
So here&#39;s an important characteristic.
If you multiply, if you take the cross product of UD
and itself, so UD transpose UD, that&#39;s going
to give us the sum of squares of the columns of UD.
And if you do the math here, because U is orthogonal, it cancels out
and you are left with D squared.
So this tells us that the entries of D, if we square them,
it actually tells you the sum of squares of UD.
That is going to come in very soon.
So note that if we-- just so you can start seeing how this is useful.
If the last k entries of D are 0, that means
that we can take out k columns from U and V, then recover the Y after that.
After removing those dimensions, so we are reducing dimensions,
and we recover the data.
So we&#39;re going to see that using R code, and apply this to actual data.
So let&#39;s try that out.
First, let&#39;s start by creating this twin high data set.
It was that simulation.
You can take a quick look by plotting y1 and y2.
I&#39;m going to keep the xlim and ylim fixed.
So let me define what I want that to be.
Let&#39;s do minus 3.5 to 3.5.
So we include all the points for sure.
All right.
And there you have it.
You can see the points, the twin heights that we&#39;ve seen before.
And now what I&#39;m going to do is I&#39;m going to apply the singular value
decomposition and show you that it gives us,
it actually gives us that rotation that we saw that has those properties.
The transformation is based on an orthogonal matrix.
And it has the variability of the columns decreasing.
So we have the first dimension having much more variability than the last.
So let&#39;s just do that real quick-- svd of y.
OK.
And if I-- now, I&#39;m going to call this PC1
because it will later see that this is actually the first principal component.
I&#39;m going to look at D times V. So the U, V,
and D matrices are included in this object s.
So I&#39;m going to take the first column.
And then I&#39;m going to take the second column,
multiply by D. These are the columns of D times V.
And now we plot this.
We plot these as well.
That&#39;s not-- plot PC1, PC2.
And we see that we obtain the rotation that we have seen before.
Whoops.
PC2, sorry.
And there it is.
See the rotation that we did previously?
So the s, the singular value decomposition gives us
that rotation that was giving us the first dimension
with a lot of variability explained so that it preserved the distance.
So we&#39;re trying to get a hint of how this all is connected.
So later we&#39;ll learn that the singular value decomposition
is related to principal component that explicitly
tries to find rotations that maximize the variability explained
by the first column of the U or V matrix.
OK.
So now let&#39;s apply this.
Let&#39;s look at some real data.
It&#39;s a little bit more complicated than this simulation that we&#39;ve looked at.
I&#39;m going to load this library called tissuesGeneExpression.
And then I&#39;m going to load the data set with that same name.
This is a pretty big data set.
We can look at the dimensions of it.
It&#39;s 189 samples.
It has several tissues.
We&#39;ve seen this one in a previous video.
So the first thing I want to do real quick, just to simplify things,
is I&#39;m going to remove the units.
I want to standardize the data set.
So standardize the columns-- I&#39;m sorry, the rows.
So it would be done like this with the function scale.
I&#39;m going to do something else just so that the video goes a little faster.
I&#39;m going to only use-- let me set the seed so it can be replicated.
I&#39;m going to only use 500 rows.
You can do it with all the rows.
It should work out the same, but this will go a little faster.
So how many should we take?
500 maybe.
OK?
So there we have it.
Oop.
This is all good.
We need to get rid of this.
All right.
That should do it.
Yeah.
One more parentheses.
OK.
So now we have this scaled matrix and I&#39;m
going to apply the singular value decomposition.
There we go.
And what I want to do first is I&#39;m going to, just so you can follow along
with the math that we showed, I&#39;m going to define these letters
so it matches the notation.
Then D is-- So this returns a vector.
sd is just a vector, so I&#39;m actually going to turn into a matrix.
So it&#39;s exactly like the math.
All right.
So first thing I want to show you is that you
can reconstruct y by using a formula.
So let&#39;s just confirm that SVD actually did what we think it did.
Let&#39;s put some spaces here so you can see it better.
So it&#39;s t(V).
So that-- find these guys.
And this should give us-- this should recover y.
So let&#39;s define these residuals.
And see, these should be the same.
So let&#39;s try that.
So let&#39;s see what is the biggest residual here.
Should be a very small number, pretty much zero.
There it is.
Very, very small.
OK.
Now, next step.
Let&#39;s quickly look at the entries of D to see
if we have anything that&#39;s very, very close to zero
so we can start reducing dimensions, getting
rid of some of these dimensions.
We have 200 samples here.
Maybe we can make it a little bit-- is it 200?
Maybe.
200, 189.
So let&#39;s look at that.
So let&#39;s plot s of d.
What&#39;s going on?
S-- come on.
It&#39;s not letting me do anything.
s of d, very quickly.
And you can see already towards the end, there
seems to be some of these that are actually exactly zero.
So let&#39;s get rid of those.
So what I&#39;m going to do is I&#39;m going to define k.
Actually here, I&#39;m going to switch it from what I show you in the slides.
This is the number I keep, not the number I get rid of.
Just to make it a little simpler.
Now I&#39;m going to only-- I&#39;m going to reconstruct y,
but now I&#39;m only going to use the-- I&#39;m going
to remove those last four columns.
So this is how it would work.
So I&#39;m reducing the dimension of the problem by 4.
Not terribly exciting, but it&#39;s a start.
OK.
So now I do this.
And let&#39;s see what the residuals look like now.
Copy this guy over.
And what is the max now?
It&#39;s going to be pretty close to zero.
Look at that.
Yep.
So removing the last four columns, we keep it exactly the same.
So we&#39;ve already achieved a little bit of a reduction.
All right.
So now let&#39;s see what happens if we can do more than that.
So one of useful results coming out of the singular value decomposition
is that the entries of d actually tell us the proportion of variance that
is explained by that particular column.
So if I plot sd squared divided by the sum of all the sd squares,
and I multiply by 100, so it&#39;s percentages, that shows us
the percent explained by that column.
So we see that the first dimension of this transformation, U, this rotation,
is explaining 20% of the variability.
And it drops down quite fast.
You can see by the time we get to 100 or so, we are pretty much at zero.
So now we&#39;re going to try something a little bit more drastic.
Let&#39;s remove half of the data, half of the dimensions.
So now it&#39;s 95.
So how much do we recover now?
So what we&#39;re going to see if we, for example, plot
box plots of the residuals, now it&#39;s not going
to be zero because we actually have removed a little bit.
If we make a box plot of these residuals--
and I&#39;m going to make the ylim-- what was it, LIM?
Just to compare to the original data.
And what we see is that we have very small residual.
So we are pretty close to the original y, even when we
reduce the dimensions by a half.
And this transformation let&#39;s us do that.
So we can actually answer what percent we actually keep by computing that.
So we could take the variance of the residuals
and divide it by the variance of the original y.
Actually, I think we have to turn this into vectors because they&#39;re matrices.
Let&#39;s do that.
And we see that we recover a lot.
It&#39;s more than 90%, right?
So that&#39;s 4% is what we lose.
So this is how much we explain.
Almost 96% by reducing the dimensions by a half.
And we didn&#39;t have to do this complicated computation because we
already have that answer just by looking at the d&#39;s.
You can take 1 through k.
We didn&#39;t have to compute residuals because the d&#39;s answer exactly
that question.
All of them.
All we have to square it.
OK.
And that should actually give us the same answer, 95.8%.
So 1 minus-- oop, sorry.
No min-- like that.
There it is.
See?
Actually, it&#39;s the exact same number.
All right.
So we could give other examples of how this is useful.
One thing we could do is create a highly correlated matrix
and see that the dimension reduction is even more greater.
In a later video, we&#39;re going to talk about multi-dimensional scaling, which
uses these results to make exploratory plots, exploratory data analysis
plots of high dimensional data, taking advantage
of these properties of the singular value decomposition.
But just to give a final example, we&#39;ll very quickly create a simulation
where we have highly correlated data.
I&#39;m going to create a vector rnorm.
It&#39;s with 100 data points.
And now I&#39;m going to create an error structure.
Yeah, let&#39;s do a bigger one-- 25 columns.
And let&#39;s just add some noise here, but a very small amount of noise.
So it&#39;s practically the same data with a little bit of change.
That&#39;s what y&#39;s going to be Actually, let&#39;s just do two.
OK.
So now I want to do two.
And what we see is that if it&#39;s something like this,
you can very quickly see, this side is very correlated, very correlated.
You could see that the singular value decomposition, if we compute it
for this thing, for this particular data set,
you get that a lot of the variabil-- almost all of the variability
is in the first column.
So let&#39;s just do this.
Oh, yeah.
Pretty much all of it.
So when you have highly correlated data like that,
you can reduce the dimensions greatly.
And you can create an example with more columns that are highly correlated
and get a similar answer.
OK.
So that should start giving you an idea of how the singular value
decomposition is useful.
We&#39;re going to keep using it in data analyses,
and you&#39;re going to start getting even more of a feeling for that.