RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In this video, we&#39;re going to briefly describe
the mathematics between rotations.
This is very related to our previous video on projections.
So, as we saw in that video, we can take an example into two dimensions.
The vector 2,3, which is shown here on the right, as a point in space.
And we can write that as a multiplication of two
coordinates, two and three, and the bases 1 and 0 and 0 and 1.
But notice that we don&#39;t have to write it this way.
We can write the vector 2,3 in other ways.
So here we change the bases to 1,1 0.5, minus 0.5.
This gives us the average and the difference.
And what we see here is that the coordinates are now 2.5 and minus 1.
So the coordinates change, but the point is the same.
That&#39;s because the coordinate system changes as well.
Now, typically, we like to use bases that are orthogonal
and that their sum of squares is one.
So we would just multiply these by the square root of 2
and divide the other by the square root of 2 to get
this alternative coordinate system.
And now our new coordinates are basically the same,
but they&#39;re shifted.
And then linear algebra gives us the rotation.
This is defined by the matrix A. And you can go back and forth
between the original data, Y, and the new coordinate,
Z. You can just go back and forth by multiplying by A.
And this is, using our example from twins,
is literally rotating the data, in this case, 45 degrees.
And you can see it going back and forth, just by multiplying by A.
So this is what we call a rotation in mathematics.