RAFAEL IRIZARRY: This is High Dimensional Data Analysis.
In this course, we&#39;re going to learn several techniques that
are necessary to properly analyze some of the data sets
that are being generated by life science researchers.
So this is going to include techniques such as principal component
analysis, singular value decomposition, some of the mathematics
that you need to understand that, like projections and rotations.
We&#39;re going to learn the mathematical the concept of distance,
then permit us to learn about clustering, a little bit of machine
learning, smoothing techniques, and then we&#39;re
going to finish it off by learning about one
of the biggest challenges today in high dimensional data,
which are batch effects.
We&#39;re going to learn what they are and some
of the statistical techniques that exist for attacking this problem.