RAFAEL IRIZARRY: When you&#39;re working with high dimensional data,
one of the techniques we use to facilitate
data exploration and other analyses is dimension reduction.
In this video, we&#39;re going to motivate the techniques
that we use for reducing data size without losing too much information.
So just to give you an example of why we would
want to do this, consider a typical high throughput experiment,
where you have 10,000 genes and 200 samples,
and we want to examine the relationship between each pair of samples.
That&#39;s a lot of scatter plots to look through.
But using data dimension reduction will show you
how this can help, for example, perform data exploration.
But there are other advantages to using this technique.
So the general idea is to reduce the dimensions of the data
set, but yet, at the same time, preserving important properties
such as-- and that&#39;s what we&#39;re going to be focusing on in this video--
the distance between samples.
So we are going to be using the concept of distance
that we have previously described.
So just to give you an example of how this could be useful,
we could somehow reduce the dimensions to just two
and we can make a plot because we know how to plot two dimensions.
You make a scatter plot.
And I&#39;ll point out, from now, that the techniques--
those mathematical techniques behind all this-- is something
called a singular value decomposition, SVD.
So we&#39;re going to be motivating the SVD here in this video.
And it&#39;s also important to remember that,
although there&#39;s complicated mathematical ideas behind all this,
what we&#39;re going to show you today gives you the intuition as to why we do it
and why it works.
And I&#39;ll also note that what we&#39;re talking about today
relates to principal component analysis and we&#39;ll
see how that all comes together later.
So to motivate the exposition here, I&#39;m going
to take this data set that I have simulated.
It&#39;s supposed to be the heights of twins.
So each point is the height of twin number one and twin number two
that it has been standardized, so this a number of standard deviations
away from the average of each twin.
So I want you to focus on the two orange points.
So we&#39;re going to calculate the distance between these points.
You see, we draw a line and you measure the length of that line.
And we know how to do that.
What we&#39;re going to try to do is we&#39;re going
to try to provide a reduction of the data set here--
it&#39;s just two dimensions-- so that we have just one dimension.
And we can summarize distance between points with just one dimension.
So to make the connection to what we are doing in the other data
sets in this course, think of this as a high throughput gene
expression data, where the twin pairs represent end sample.
So each pair of twins is a sample.
And the two measurements you have, the two heights,
are two expressions for two genes.
So imagine that instead of-- you know, we have 20,000 genes
and reduce the reduction-- in this very simple example,
we&#39;re trying to reduce the dimensions from two to one.
But the ideas that we use to do that actually extrapolate to larger data
sets.
One of the things I want you to note is that if you
try to compute the distance between any two points in this figure,
you will see that most of the lines that go between two points
are kind of going on a diagonal.
So if we were able to somehow rotate this picture so
that that distance between the points is now in one of the dimensions,
and we would be very close to our ultimate goal of reducing this down
to one dimension.
So let&#39;s see how we would do that.
All right, so let&#39;s consider an example.
The distance between those two points is actually 1.14
and we can compute the distance for every pair.
And again, we&#39;re going to try to summarize or reduce
the dimensions of this data set to just one and preserve this distance.
All right.
So here&#39;s one idea.
Let&#39;s perform a transformation that is actually intuitive.
Instead of plotting the heights against each other,
we&#39;re going to plot the difference on the y-axis and the average
on the x-axis.
So we can already see that the distance between the averages
is already a summary of a distance that is just one dimensional.
If you just compute the distance between the averages,
now you have reduced it to one dimension.
The transformation we&#39;re going to end up with
is similar to what we&#39;ve just shown.
So now another important point is that when
we do this, when we perform this transformation, when we take the two
heights and we convert them into the average and the difference
between heights, we can represent this with linear algebra.
It&#39;s a linear transformation, as shown in this slide.
And you can see that just by having a simple two by two matrix,
you can transform the data from the original Y-matrix, which
is what I want to call it, to a new matrix, Z.
And by taking the inverse of A, you can transform back.
So you lose no information going back between Z and Y.
So here&#39;s a plot again.
On the left, you have Y1 versus Y2.
And on the right, you have Z2 versus Z1.
OK.
So now we&#39;re going to look at this a little bit more closely.
If we compute the standard deviations of the Z&#39;s-- right, so if you take each Z,
individually, and you think of the Y&#39;s as coming from, say,
a distribution that has standard deviation sigma,
well the first dimension is the average.
So now, the standard deviation is 1 over the square root of 2 times sigma.
Well the y-axis, in this case, Z2, is a difference of Y&#39;s.
And this is the square of 2 times sigma.
So we have performed a transformation that
changes the standard deviations of the two dimensions.
Before, they were the same, and now they&#39;re different.
And that is a little bit of a problem for what
we want to do later, where we want to preserve these overall variabilities.
So what we can do, it&#39;s easy to fix.
We just multiply 1 by the square root of 2.
And the other one, we divide by the square root of 2.
And now we have a transformation where the standard deviations are preserved.
And it&#39;s shown in this slide with A, right?
It&#39;s 1 over square root of 2 times the matrix 1, 1, 1, minus 1.
So if we multiply by this matrix instead,
we preserve the standard deviations.
Notice that this is an orthogonal matrix.
A inverse, A transpose A is the identity.
And that actually is why the standard deviations are preserved.
So if I perform this transformation, because it
is an orthogonal transformation-- here, I&#39;m
showing you the R code that would do it--
if I compute the distance between each point in Y,
compute the distance between each point using the Z&#39;s, and we
plot those against each other-- this is a plot of all the distances
from the Z&#39;s and all the distances from the Y&#39;s, you
can see they&#39;re exactly the same.
This is a mathematical fact.
The distances are preserved.
So this transformation preserves distances between points,
unlike the first one we saw, the difference versus the average.
So now we can plot this.
And you can see it&#39;s a rotation.
You take the data, that starts with a scatter like this,
and we have rotated it to have the data with the dimension on the first axis
that&#39;s related to the average and a dimension
on the y-axis that&#39;s related to the difference.
So what we&#39;re going to do now is we&#39;re going to note that in the second plot,
the second dimension adds very little information.
If you were going to compute the distance between two points,
the distance computed just on the Z&#39;s are almost all you need.
Look at the two orange points, for example.
They almost have the same value of Z2.
Therefore, the distance is mostly driven by the distance
in just the first dimension.
And that actually holds true for all the points.
If we compute the distance based only on the first dimension--
we completely ignore the second dimension of Z.
So now we&#39;ve reduced it to just one dimension.
We compute the distance.
We plot them against each other.
We see that we get a very close approximation.
This is, basically, the ideas behind what
is called principal component analysis.
Also, it&#39;s very related to the singular value decomposition.
So one of the things I want to point out before we finish here
is that if you look for explanations of the principal component analysis,
you will notice that the explanations are a little bit off compared
to what we&#39;ve just seen here.
And that&#39;s because, typically, the units--
in the standard statistical analysis, the units are in the rows.
In genomics, for reasons that we&#39;re not going to explain here,
the units are typically in the columns.
So if you look at an explanation that you look up on PCA,
you&#39;ll probably see everything transposed.
But other than that, you will see that this matches those explanations.