RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Now that we&#39;ve learned how the SVD works,
we&#39;re going to use that to create an MDS plot, a Multi-Dimensional Scale plot.
So what I&#39;m going to do is I&#39;m going to apply it to a version, a subset,
of our matrix that has the tissue gene expression that we&#39;ve
been working with.
I&#39;m only going to look at kidney, colon, and liver, just to keep it simple.
And what I&#39;m going to do first is I&#39;m going to compute the singular value
decomposition on this subset.
On the subset of the matrix, it has only 99 columns,
because it, again, only uses these three issues.
OK.
So I want to make a plot.
I want to be able to plot all these samples
and see how close they are to each other.
I want to see if kidneys are closer to kidneys than colons, all that stuff.
OK?
So I can&#39;t make a picture of two points that have 22,000 dimensions.
I&#39;m going to use singular value decomposition,
and I&#39;m going to look at the two dimensions that
have the most variability, the columns have the most variability.
So what we saw in this video is that we can take the SVD of mat.
Now, I&#39;m going to remove the means.
I&#39;m going to de-trend them in this sense,
because I don&#39;t want the differences in means to contribute to the variability
that I&#39;m capturing here.
When you compute distance between two columns, the mean of the genes
doesn&#39;t come in, because they cancel out when you subtract them from each other.
All right?
So I&#39;m going to take this SVD.
Look at how fast this is.
Done.
OK.
And now what I&#39;m going to do is I&#39;m going to reconstruct the z matrix that
has just two dimensions.
And the way we did that is we saw this formula that
gave us this way of doing it, right?
So we take just the first two columns.
That is z-- oh, I need to add the s here.
And now we can see that this z, as I mentioned, 2 by 99.
So instead of 22,215 dimensions, now I&#39;m down to two.
And I&#39;m ready to make pictures.
Now, I&#39;m going to transform the z, just because I am more used to plotting
when I have things in columns.
But there&#39;s no reason to do that.
I&#39;m just used to it doing that that way.
OK.
Now I can plot.
So for example, then you can do this.
All right?
So you can see all the points here.
And now, the idea is that if I want to know the distance between two
columns of mat-- these are 22 dimensional vectors,
so, really, it&#39;s not easy to do.
I, instead, in this visualization, the idea
is that distance is approximated by the distance between points in this plot.
So now I can visualize it.
That&#39;s the power of this approach.
So let&#39;s look at this a little bit closer.
So I&#39;m actually going to add this library
to make it a little nicer-looking.
And now I can plot z.
All right.
So you see the points.
And now, what do you think these three clusters are?
Well, let&#39;s add some color to this and see.
I&#39;m going to add the tissue as color.
And let&#39;s see what we have.
Well, there you go.
So we have the tissues separate out as we expected.
So that is a great feature.
Now, we don&#39;t only have to restrict ourselves to the first two dimensions.
For example, we can look at the third and the fourth.
Here&#39;s the third and the fourth.
OK?
And now, we do that instead.
And we see something different.
Now we have another source of variability here.
And you can see that one of these tissues, the orange tissue,
is splitting up into two.
That could be sex, for example.
It could be some other variable.
But it also has quite a bit of variability.
But not as much as tissue-to-tissue variability.
That was the strongest one.
It seemed to capture the first two columns of the singular value
decomposition.
Now, one other quick thing is that we don&#39;t
have to do this with the singular value decomposition.
There&#39;s a function called the CMD in R. It&#39;s the multi-dimensional scaling plot
function that gets you that.
So if I compute the distance between things,
then it uses cmdscale to approximate the distances.
And then we get practically the same picture.
Well I don&#39;t want this to be so big.
Let&#39;s get rid of that.
But yeah.
We get the same plot.
It&#39;s doing practically the same thing.
Another little point is that you can change the K. K2 is a default.
So it only gives you two dimensions.
But you could change this to four or five or six, and get as many dimensions
as you want from the SVD approach, the columns of u and v.
OK.
So that&#39;s how multi-dimensional scaling is done in R,
and how it relates to the singular value decomposition.