RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Now that we know what hierarchical clustering is,
we&#39;re ready to explain heat maps and show you how to make them in R.
So the idea behind a heat map is to show you the data in two dimensions.
We&#39;re using color.
So for example, if I could just use a image function
to show you the first 100 genes, and it would look like this,
I have to load the data.
And you can see that that&#39;s what the image is.
And the yellow means high, red means low.
And you can see every cell in this picture,
every little pixel, like you see this little square here,
represents one entry in the table, and the color represents the number.
Now, what the heat map does, it adds structure to this data.
It clusters the genes and it clusters the samples,
and then creates an image like this.
That&#39;s what a heat map does.
So if we wanted to make the heat map for this data set,
we can&#39;t just run it on the entire data set because then we
would get 22,000 rows, and that is not something we can see on a screen.
We don&#39;t even have enough pixels on the screen to see that.
And certainly, our eyes can&#39;t distinguish 22,000 times 189
as a matrix of pixels.
So many times, when you make a heat map in practice,
you&#39;re going to choose some genes, some rows, to show.
One very standard way to do that is to pick genes that vary a lot.
You can take the top, say-- I&#39;m going to make a small heat map.
So I&#39;ll take the first 40 genes of how much they vary.
There&#39;s other ways to do that.
I&#39;m going to do that here quickly so that you can see how that works.
I&#39;m going to take the top 40 genes that vary the most using the rowVars
function to get those, and I&#39;m going to subset the e matrix using those genes.
And now I can just call the heatmap function like this,
and it&#39;ll make a heat map.
I don&#39;t have to transpose the heat in any way.
So there you go.
It already made it.
So it clustered the genes here.
It clustered the samples, and then it renders the plot
with the colors representing the measurements.
So we can see, for example, that these genes are highly
expressed in whatever cluster that is, and these genes are low expressed
in whatever cluster of samples that is.
Now, right now, the plot isn&#39;t very informative.
I&#39;m going to show you slowly how to add to it.
Now, the first thing I want to do is change the colors.
I don&#39;t like yellow and red too much, so I&#39;m going to use this R color brewer
package to pick some colors.
So here&#39;s a standard way you do that.
You can run the-- let me make this a little bigger so you can see it.
I&#39;m going to use the brewer.pal function.
You can look at the Help file.
So you can see all the choices there are for the palettes.
Green to blue is one.
We&#39;re going to take that one.
And then I&#39;m going to use this color ramp palette, which
is a function that takes these nine colors
and creates 100 consecutive colors that slowly goes from the first one
to the last.
That&#39;s how that works.
And now I have new colors, and I can rerun this command using those.
Let me copy it here and run it again with these colors.
And you can see that they&#39;re a little bit better to look at.
So now we have low expression is white and high expression is blue.
All right.
Now what else can we do here?
First of all, I&#39;ll say that the heat map function I actually don&#39;t like to use.
The main reason is that when I stretch out the plot, it always stays the same
and doesn&#39;t reshape itself.
So there&#39;s another alternative called the heatmap.2 function that
works much better than heatmap, and I&#39;m going
to show you how you can use it here.
So it&#39;s in the gplots package.
I load that up.
I have to redo the colors.
So, yeah.
Oh yeah.
So the next thing I&#39;m going to do is I&#39;m going
to create a palette of colors for the different tissues
because it&#39;s very hard to read these samples here, these sample names here.
So I&#39;m going to add color to represent the different tissues,
and that&#39;ll visually let me see it.
So the way I&#39;m going to do that is I&#39;m going
to create a palette with eight colors.
I can use seven.
There&#39;s only seven tissues.
And then assign to each one-- to each tissue, you get assigned one color.
So let&#39;s look at how that works.
I have to load up rafalib to get as.fumeric.
Oops, library.
And now you can see that colors, you can see
that-- it&#39;s a little hard to read-- but you can see that they&#39;re repeats.
That&#39;s because they&#39;re the same tissue.
Now, one way to see that is to do this.
We can show the tissue.
So there we can see a table.
And you can see this column name, the tissue, and the color.
These are the way you define colors in R more generally.
And you can see the endometrium has the same color.
Liver has all the same color, et cetera.
So I&#39;m going to use that as what&#39;s called the labCol, the column
lab, the color for the lab.
Now, I&#39;m sorry.
The column side colors I&#39;m going to define as cols.
I&#39;m going to give these colors are the color for the heat map.
We already defined that.
I&#39;m going to then add, instead of the column names,
I&#39;m going to use tissue as the column name
so I can see that the different names-- liver, endometrium, et cetera.
And now I&#39;m ready to go.
And then one last thing.
Trace, I don&#39;t want to trace.
You can look at the Help file for what trace is.
I never make heat maps with trace I don&#39;t recommend using that in general.
All right.
So let&#39;s see how that looks.
And you&#39;ll see how much nicer it looks than before.
Now I can stretch it.
And you can see how the entire plot stretches out when you do that.
You can see the livers, the cerebellums, but it&#39;s still
hard to read because they&#39;re so tiny, but now I have the color.
So these are all the same tissue.
These are all the same tissues, et cetera.
So that&#39;s how I use heat maps in R, and hopefully it&#39;ll
be a useful tool for you to explore your high dimensional data.