PROFESSOR IRIZARRY: We&#39;re ready to perform machine learning in R. So what
we&#39;re going to try to do is we&#39;re going to try to predict tissues
based on gene expression data.
And as we&#39;ll see later, we&#39;re going to make
it a little bit challenging because it turns out
that that&#39;s a very easy thing to do.
Tissues have very different gene expression profiles.
So we&#39;ll try to do it with fewer dimensions than all the genes.
Now, before we start, I want to show you the outcome
that we&#39;re trying to predict.
It&#39;s tissue.
So we can see that there&#39;s one tissue placenta that only has six.
So I&#39;m actually going to take that one out.
And that way it gives us a little bit more balance.
And it&#39;s better for illustration purposes.
But there are ways to implement machine learning
algorithms with cases like this.
So let&#39;s take out the columns with that tissue that&#39;s your placenta.
And then we will define y, our outcome of interest,
and x, our matrix of predictors.
So y is tissue categories.
And x is the transpose of e.
It&#39;s the transpose because each column now is a predictor.
That&#39;s how these machine learning algorithms work.
So we can see the dimension of x is the number of outcomes-- 183--
that&#39;s the length of y.
And it has 22,215 predictors.
Now, the first thing we think about when we&#39;re
getting ready to do machine learning is cross validation.
So it&#39;s very important that we cross validate our results that we
train on one set and test on another.
So the first thing I&#39;m going to do is create a set of indices
that facilitates cross validation.
And we&#39;re going to use this nice, little function in the caret package
to create folds.
It automatically does this for us.
So it takes our outcome y, and we&#39;re going to create five folds.
So what it does is it splits the data into five groups.
And now what we&#39;re going to do, which are called the folds.
And what we&#39;re going to do when we come to the prediction part
is we&#39;re going to leave out one fold, use the other four to train,
and then test on that one we left out.
That&#39;s the idea behind cross validation.
And then we do that for each fold.
We leave out the first, the second, the third, the fourth, and the fifth.
Let&#39;s show you what the outcomes are in these five folds.
So have five folds.
And in each one, we have a series of tissues.
These are the tissues in the five subsets.
The number of tissues in each of the five subsets.
You can see why we left placenta out.
A lot of these would have zero placentas.
And it would complicate the problem slightly.
Now, as I said earlier, we&#39;re going to make this problem more challenging
by looking at only two dimensions.
We&#39;re going to take the first two dimensions that
is given to us by cmdscale.
So we&#39;re going to make a smaller set of predictors, basically, two.
And we&#39;re going to try to predict tissues based on these two predictors.
So I&#39;m going to load the rafalib package to make some nice looking pictures.
And you can see what these two dimensions are.
And there they are.
And we have the different colors or the different tissues.
So we&#39;re going to try to predict those colors based on these two dimensions.
You can already see that it&#39;s not going to be easy, because they
don&#39;t separate out perfect.
All right, so let&#39;s get started.
So I&#39;m going to use knn to do this, which is in the library class.
And I&#39;m going to apply knn in the following way.
What I do is I-- I&#39;m going to train on the rows-- on all the rows except the ith
fold.
So here I&#39;m doing the first one.
So I&#39;m going to take out the rows that are
indexed in that first fold-- take them out-- take them out also
for the outcome y.
You can see here-- cl gives us the outcome.
And then we&#39;re going to test on the remaining dataset.
So that gives us back-- we&#39;re going to get back results for this test data
as well.
So we don&#39;t use the indices in this fold to train the model.
So that&#39;s our test set.
So we can run this quick.
It&#39;s very fast.
And now we can see how we did.
So we can look at the tissues and the actual tissues and the calls.
And we can see, for example, that we made some mistakes for cerebellum.
There&#39;s two mistakes here.
I think we got all our colons right.
But we got some errors in the hippocampus.
We can just tally up all the mistakes we made here.
We count how many mistakes we made.
And we take the mean.
And we see that 17%-- we made mistakes in 17% of our predictions.
Now that was only one fold.
So now the next step is to run through this,
do the same at the same thing we just did-- do it now for every fold.
So that&#39;s what I&#39;m going to do now.
I&#39;m going to go along each of the five folds.
This is just one through five.
See that there.
And for each one, I&#39;m going to run again--
what we just did-- I&#39;m going to run it again leaving out now
the first, second, third, fourth and fifth fold
and then counting the number of mistakes we made.
So we just run that.
I&#39;m going to do that for the first-- so I don&#39;t this i anymore.
Where did I go?
I&#39;m sorry-- right down here.
So I don&#39;t need to-- the i is set in sapply.
And I do need to set k because I am naming in general.
You&#39;ll see why we&#39;re doing that in a second to let&#39;s say five.
Now we run it.
Now we are doing, again, we&#39;re doing the cross validation.
Basically, we&#39;re testing and training, leaving out folds,
and we&#39;re doing it for all five.
We run this-- should be pretty quick.
And now we have in res.k-- the results.k--
we can see we made six mistakes in each one of them.
Now the next step is to compare the different k.
So we want to choose the number of nearest neighbors that we include.
Is 5 a good choice?
Or should we have done 10?
Shoud we have done 1?
So before we continue with that, let&#39;s write down
here what the final outcome is.
We sum up res.k and divide by the length of y.
And that gives us the error rate-- 16% now.
I&#39;m going to do this now-- not for every single k, but several k.
So let&#39;s do 1 through 12.
And now what I do is I add another level of another loop.
I go through the k&#39;s-- function(k).
And I&#39;m ready to apply what we just did for these 12 values of k.
And then we can plot them and see which one works best.
Then we close it.
All right, so there it&#39;s pretty fast.
And now we can just plot k&#39;s against this res and see how they compare.
And we can see that the best choice actually was five.
And we can see that 0 makes more mistakes.
And then it goes up.
So that&#39;s how we use cross validation to do the prediction.
And with just two dimensions, we did OK.
16% mistakes is not terrible.
Now the last thing I want to show you here
is that we use more-- if we use more samples-- sorry, if we
use more than two dimensions, then it becomes pretty easy to do this.
So we can see that.
If I now redo it with five dimensions instead of two,
we can see that-- let&#39;s wait for it to finish and then run it.
So we use five dimensions.
Before we used two in the k nearest neighbors approach.
Then we do much, much better.
We basically make no mistakes when we have more dimensions.
So just with five dimensions, we&#39;re already doing a very good job.
If we make it 100 or 1,000 dimensions, then we&#39;ll probably do perfect.
So that&#39;s how you use cross validation to test out machine learning procedures
and also to pick the parameters.